A Guide to the Harry Lyons Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Harry Lyons Collection 1948-1987
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
Acc 23
6.4 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Dr. Lyons over a span of several years. It includes accessioning numbers Acc 23, Acc 77, Acc 86, PF-176, PF-181, PF-182, PF-183 and 88/Mar/13.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Harry Lyons was born in Washington DC on March 18, 1900. His father moved the family to Lexington, Virginia when Lyons was a year old. It was in Lexington that he was raised and went to school. After a year at Washington and Lee University in the Student Army Training Corps, he followed his sister's advice and transferred to the Medical College of Virginia where he graduated with a degree in dentistry in 1923.
Impressed with his strong knowledge, Dr. Cameron Hoogan, Dean of the School of Dentistry, offered Lyons a faculty position right after graduation. Remembering a professor's comparison of the beauty of a bicuspid to a young girl, Lyons decided to make an engagement ring out of a tooth in a black vulcanite setting. Sara Miriam Wice would accept his unusual ring and they were married for 41 years until her death in 1967.
Lyons worked as a full-time faculty member until 1928 when he started his own practice in periodontics. He continued to teach part time until 1950, progressing through the academic ranks to become a professor of periodontia and oral pathology. He would eventually become the periodontal department chair. Then in 1951, he accepted a challenge from MCV President Dr. William Sanger, to create the best dental school in the country, and became Dean of the School of Dentistry.
Lyons was active professionally and served as president of several state and national dental associations including the American Academy of Periodontology, the American Association of Dental Schools, and the American Dental Association. It was during his tenure as President of the ADA that the issue of fluoridation of water became a national debate. Lyons was frequently quoted in the press advocating the benefits of fluoridation. He was called to testify before several state legislatures as well as the United State Congress. In the end, Lyons efforts were successful as many states adopted his recommendations adding this element to their community water supplies.
Lyons was a prolific writer and contributor to dental literature with over thirty articles to his credit. These range from specific clinical dental procedures to advice on professional behavior and grooming.. Lyons continued to teach classes even after he became Dean. Lyons disliked facial hair and forbid MCV students from having moustaches and beards for years during his tenure. While Dean, Lyons wrote about the relationship between research and education, including ways to improve dental instruction. Lyons twice earned the William J. Gies award for the best paper in the Journal of Dental Research.
Throughout his career Lyons was recognized for his hard work and dedication to the dental profession. He received Distinguished Service Awards from four national dental associations. He was named a Laurate of Virginia, and given the Edward Wayne Medal for outstanding service to Virginia Commonwealth University in 1981. After over fifty years of dedication to MCV, Lyons was awarded the Outstanding Alumnus Award in 1985. He also held four honorary doctoral degrees. Lyons married Doris Yingling, Dean of the School of Nursing in 1969.
Lyons retired as Dean in 1970, and was named Dean Emeritus. That same year, the new dental building was named in his honor. In addition VCU has named a scholarship, professorship, and an outstanding dental alumni award in his honor. Lyons established several endowments including a fund to support the School of Dentistry, libraries, and the VCU Center for Judaic Studies.
Lyons died April 15, 1997 and was buried in Hebrew Cemetery in Richmond, VA. At the time of his death, the School of Dentistry was ranked as one of the top ten in the country.
Scope and Content
The collection focuses on Lyons' writings, articles, clippings, photographs, and awards covering his professional career and tenure as Dean of the School of Dentistry, Medical College of Virginia, 1948-1979. The body of the collection is his papers and addresses. Lyons professional work was in periodontology, which deals with diseases of the gums These papers focus on problems and solutions related to this specialty, improving dental education, professional ethics. The collection also chronicles his gifts to the University and donations to local organizations. The collection does not include information regarding Lyons private dental practice or the official record of the School of Dentistry.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Biography
  This series contains a biography as well as early personal records.
  - Biography (Box-folder 1.1)
    This folder contains a biography, publications list, selected bibliography and several newspaper clippings with biographic information.
  - Elementary and High School records 1907-1917 (Box-folder 1.2)
    Original school records bound in a binder
  - Army discharge papers, MCV documents. 1918-1925 (Box-folder 1.3)
    Grades, early employment documents, and Army discharge paperwork.
- Correspondence 1924-1979
  Letters on a wide variety of subjects. Most are personal or are related to Lyons' work with his many dental associations.
  - Undated (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Correspondence 1924-1958 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Correspondence 1959-1966 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Correspondence 1967-1978 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Correspondence 1979 (Box-folder 2.5)
- Subject Files
  This series include varied subjects and papers. Each is organized either by event, organization, or person.
  - Albert Einstein Medical Center, Philadelphia PA April 5, 1959 (Box-folder 3.1)
    Dental Clinic Dedicatory Address.
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity December 30, 1956 (Box-folder 3.2)
    Achievement Award, Life membership card. (Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - American Academy of Periodontology November 4, 1954 (Box-folder 3.3)
    President's Address. (Audio on cassette)
  - American Association of Dental Examiners 1957 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - American Association of Dental Schools 1961-1965 (Box-folder 3.5)
    This folder contains correspondence and speeches given during these years.
  - American Association of Dental Schools. 1964 (Box-folder 3.6)
    Bound volume, Proceedings of the 41st Annual Meeting
  - American Association of Dental Schools. 1954 (Box-folder 3.7)
    Committee on Social Trends in Professional Relations report.
  - American College of Dentists. 1951 (Box-folder 3.8)
    Convocation, Washington D.C.
  - American College of Dentists. 1962 -1965 (Box-folder 3.9)
    See Gies Award, 1978
  - American Dental Association 1957 (Box-folder 3.10)
    President's Reports
  - American Dental Association 1939 (Box-folder 3.11)
    81st Annual Session. Milwaukee, WI
  - American Dental Association 1957 (Box-folder 3.12)
    98th Annual Session. Miami, FL
  - American Dental Association 1961 (Box-folder 3.13)
    102nd Annual Session. Philadelphia, PA. (see folder 4.28)
  - American Dental Association 1956 (Box-folder 3.14)
    Conference on Dental Research. Atlantic City, NJ
  - American Dental Association 1960 (Box-folder 3.15)
    Conference of National Organizations for Areas of Dental Practice. Chicago, IL
  - American Dental Association 1966-1969 (Box-folder 3.16)
    Council on Dental Education.
  - American Dental Association 1980 (Box-folder 3.17)
    Distinguished Service Award.
  - American Dental Association (Box-folder 3.18)
    Miscellaneous
  - American Dental Trade Association. 1955-1964 (Box-folder 3.19)
  - American Fund for Dental Health. 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3.20)
    1st Annual Founders' Award
  - American Fund for Dental Health. 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3.21)
  - Arizona State Boards. 1963-1966 (Box-folder 3.22)
  - Baylor College of Dentistry 1973 (Box-folder 3.23)
    Commencement Address. See Folder 9.3
  - Belgian Dental Congress 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3.24)
    Brussels, Belguim
  - Canadian Dental Association 1956 (Box-folder 3.25)
    Annual Meeting. Banff, Alberta, Canada (See folder 6.2)
  - Case Reports 1934-1950 (Box-folder 3.26)
    Photographs, x-rays and reports concerning individual cases Lyons worked on while in private practice.
  - Congregation Beth Ahabah 1937-1975 (Box-folder 3.27)
    President Reports
  - Correspondence, General 1976-1987 (Box-folder 3.27)
  - Federation Dentaire Internationale 1957-1959, 1964 (Box-folder 3.29)
  - Federation Dentaire Internationale 1955 (Box-folder 3.30)
    43rd Annual Meeting. Copenhagen, Denmark
  - Florida Board of Examiners 1966-1970 (Box-folder 3.31)
    Correspondence
  - Florida Board of Examiners 1964-1968 (Box-folder 3.32)
    Clippings and exhibits.
  - Fluoridation 1957-1959 (Box-folder 3.33)
  - Geis, William J. Award 1965-1966 (Box-folder 3.34)
    American Academy of Periodontology
  - Geis, William J. Award 1978 (Box-folder 3.35)
    American College of Dentists
  - Hebrew University - Hadassah School of Dentistry 1959-1966 (Box-folder 3.36)
  - Hill, Senator Lister. 1961 (Box-folder 3.37)
    Citation, American College of Dentists
  - International Conference on Dental Education and Dental Research. 1959 (Box-folder 3.38)
    New York, NY
  - James, E. John 1935 (Box-folder 3.39)
  - Joint Session: (AADS-IADR) 1958 (Box-folder 3.40)
    Detroit, MI
  - Kentucky Dental Association 1960 (Box-folder 3.41)
    Centennial Meeting. Lexington, KY
  - Letterheads (Box-folder 3.42)
  - Licensure 1956-1959 (Box-folder 3.43)
    This folder includes correspondence involving various state and national licensing boards
  - "The Lion of Dentistry" 1956 (Box-folder 3.44)
    Indiana Dental School
  - "H. Lyons Collection" (Box-folder 3.45)
  - Maimonides Award 1978 (Box-folder 3.46)
    Health Services award, State of Israel.
  - Massachusetts Dental Society 1964 (Box-folder 3.47)
    Centennial Meeting. Boston, MA
  - Mid-Continent Dental Congress 1956 (Box-folder 3.48)
    15th Annual Meeting. St. Louis, MO
  - Miscellany 1919-1978 (Box-folder 3.49)
  - Miscellany 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3.50)
  - Nagle, Raymond F. 1965-1967 (Box-folder 3.51)
    Dean, New York School of Dentistry.
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews 1966 (Box-folder 3.52)
    Brotherhood Citation
  - National Conference of the Joint Council to Improve the Health of the Aged. 1959 (Box-folder 3.53)
  - New York University 1965 (Box-folder 3.54)
    Honorary Degree.
  - NYU, New York College of Dentistry 1965 (Box-folder 3.55)
    Centennial celebration. New York, NY
  - North Carolina Dental Association 1954 (Box-folder 3.56)
    Annual Meeting. Pinehurst, NC
  - Ohio State Dental Association 1956 (Box-folder 3.57)
    91st Annual Meeting. Columbus, OH
  - Omicron Delta Kappa 1973 (Box-folder 3.58)
    Honorary Initiation
  - Pilcher, Dr. William 1931, 1934 (Box-folder 3.59)
  - Richmond Dental Society 1956 (Box-folder 3.60)
    33 year in the Society.
  - Richmond, Department of Public Health. City Dental Clinics 1962-1970 (Box-folder 3.61)
  - Robinson, J. Ben 1953-1964 (Box-folder 3.62)
    Testimonials, correspondence.
  - Talley, Frank E. (Box-folder 3.63)
  - Tel Aviv University 1977 (Box-folder 3.64)
    Board of Governors
  - Tel Aviv University 1977 (Box-folder 3.65)
    Miscellany
  - Temple University 1956 (Box-folder 3.66)
    Honorary Degree. Philadelphia, PA
  - "Two Centuries of Dentistry in Virginia" 1976 (Box-folder 3.67)
    Virginia Dental Association Fellowship(Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - US Army Dental Corps 1961-1967 (Box-folder 3.68)
    Consultant to..
  - U.S. Army Walter Reed Army Institute of Research 1956-1963 (Box-folder 3.69)
  - U.S. Food and Drug Administration 1950-1961 (Box-folder 3.70)
    Consultant to...
  - U.S. House Subcommittee on Legal and Monetary Affairs 1958 (Box-folder 3.71)
    This folder deals with attempts to regulate ads for toothpaste.
  - U.S. National Advisory Council on Education for Health Professionals 1964-1967 (Box-folder 3.72)
    This folder includes information on the promotion of dental education
  - U.S. National Advisory Dental Research Council 1953-1957 (Box-folder 3.73)
  - U.S. National Advisory Dental Research Council 1961-1972 (Box-folder 3.74)
  - U.S. Navy Surgeon-General 1955-1960 (Box-folder 3.75)
    Honorary Civilian Consultant
  - U.S. Senate Committee of Consultants on Medical Research 1959-1960 (Box-folder 3.76)
  - University of Manitoba 1960 (Box-folder 3.77)
    Honorary Degree, Official Opening Ceremony-School of Dentistry. Winnipeg, Manitoba
  - University of Pennsylvania 1956 (Box-folder 3.77)
    Skytop. Philadelphia, PA
  - University of Tennessee 1964 (Box-folder 3.79)
    Commencement Address. Memphis, TN
  - Veterans Administration 1962-1971 (Box-folder 3.80)
    Consultant work
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, Harry Lyons Fund for Judaic Studies 1972-1974 (Box-folder 3.81)
    This folder includes the initial paperwork involved in setting up this endowment to the University.
  - VCU-Tillie Lyons Ethics Collection Endowment 1987-1988 (Box-folder 3.82)
    This folder contains the documentation setting up this endowment to the University.
  - VCU/MCV Lyons Building: Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box-folder 3.83)
    This folder includes official correspondence in the naming of the new Dental building after Lyons, as well as personal letters of congradulations.
  - VCU/MCV Lyons Building: Miscellany 1967-1971 (Box-folder 3.84)
    The folder includes the speech, articles, invitations and other items associated with the opening of the building.
  - VCU Service Awards Program 1973, 1975 (Box-folder 3.85)
    This folder includes programs from the VCU Service Awards program.
  - VCU/MCV Alumni Association 1971 (Box-folder 3.86)
    Correspondence with Minnie Frank, Executive Secretary of the MCV Alumni Association.
  - VCU- Portrait of Harry Lyons 1955 (Box-folder 3.87)
    This folder includes correspondence and publications concerning the presentation of Lyon's portrait at the University.
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1951-1969 (Box-folder 3.88)
    Annual Reports
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1968-1970 (Box-folder 3.89)
    "Clean-shaven dental students"
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1968
    "Encouraging Excellence"
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1972 (Box-folder 3.91)
    Homecoming flyers and clipping
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1974 (Box-folder 3.92)
    Honors Convocation
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1970
    This folder contains official documents as well as personal correspondence on Lyons' retirement.
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1948-1970 (Box-folder 3.94)
    Salary records
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1974-1986 (Box-folder 3.95)
    This folder contains documents regarding the Endowment Fund
  - VCU/MCV School of Dentistry 1977 (Box-folder 3.96)
  - VCU Service Award 1964, 1975 (Box-folder 3.97)
    This folder includeds official documents and the Service Award.
  - Virginia State Dental Association 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3.98)
    Controversy
  - Virginia State Dental Association 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3.99)
  - Virginia State Dental Association 1978 (Box-folder 3.100)
    Signal Honor Award
  - Virginia State Dental Association 1957 (Box-folder 3.101)
    Testimonial to Harry Lyons.
  - Washington and Lee University 1972 (Box-folder 3.102)
    Establishment of the Max and Jennie Lyons Fund
  - Washington and Lee University 1979 (Box-folder 3.103)
    Honorary Degree. Lexington, VA
  - White House Conference on Health 1965 (Box-folder 3.104)
- Addresses and Speeches 1928-1987
  - "Achievement" 1956 (Box-folder 4.1)
    response to Alpha Omega Achievement Medal. (See folder 3.2)
  - "Acute Necrotizing Gingivitis" 1955 (Box-folder 4.2)
    Read at the 43rd Annual Meeting of the Federation Dentaire Internationale. (See Folder 3.30)
  - "Acute Nocrotizing Periodontal Disease" 1948 (Box-folder 4.3)
    Published in Journal of the American Dental Association, Vol. 37. Sept. 1948
  - The American Dental Association Research Program 1956 (Box-folder 4.4)
    (See Folder 3.14)
  - "Courses for Profit and Self-Aggrandizement" 1958 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - "A Critique of the Dental School Clinic" (Box-folder 4.6)
  - "The Crystal Ball" 1957 (Box-folder 4.7)
    Originally written as a President's Address to the American Dental Association. (See Folder 3.12, Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - "Dental Education" (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Dental Education in Relation to Dental Responsibility and Practice. (Box-folder 4.9)
  - Dental Education in the U.S. 1964 (Box-folder 4.10)
    Address given at the Belgian Dental Congress (See Folder 3.24)
  - Variations on 'Dental Licensure' (Box-folder 4.11)
    (See Folder 3.43)
  - Dentistry: Is it Traveling to the Right or the Left? 1960 (Box-folder 4.12)
    Read at the Kentucky Dental Association (See Folder 3.41)
  - Dentistry - Its Role as a Health Profession 1957 (Box-folder 4.13)
    Printed in the Arkansas and Arizona Dental Journals
  - Dentistry Peers Through a Window 1955 (Box-folder 4.14)
  - Dentistry's Future (Box-folder 4.15)
  - Drugs in Periodontal Therapy 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4.16)
    Printed in the Journal of the American Dental Association, Vol 27 Jun. 1940
  - "Essentials" 1971 (Box-folder 4.17)
    Read at the Rotary Club. Richmond, VA
  - "Fiction and Facts in Periodontology" 1949 (Box-folder 4.18)
    Printd in the Journal of the American Dental Association. Vol 39 Nov. 1949
  - "Fluoridation of Municipal Water Supplies" 1952 (Box-folder 4.18)
    (See Folder 3.33)
  - "How Do National Organizations Serve the Dental Profession?" 1960 (Box-folder 4.19)
    Read at the Annual Meeting of the American Dental Association. Chicago, IL
  - "How May the Quality of Teaching Be Evaluated?" 1956 (Box-folder 4.23)
    Read at the Mid-Coninent Dental Congress. St. Louis, MO (See Folder 3.48)
  - "Illustrated Needs for Research in Dental Therapeutics." 1947 (Box-folder 4.22)
  - "The Importance of Periodontal Diagnosis." (Box-folder 4.23)
  - "Medico-Dental Relations" 1937 (Box-folder 4.24)
  - Miscellaneous Journal and Magazine Articles. 1932-1987 (Box-folder 4.25)
  - "The Obligations of the New Dentist to Society, to his Profession and to his Fellow Dentists." 1961 (Box-folder 4.26)
    Printed in the Journal of the American Dental Association. Vol. 64 Jan. 1962
  - Opportunities in Dentistry 1961 (Box-folder 4.27)
    (See Folder 3.13, Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - "The Other Side" 1957 (Box-folder 4.28)
    Read at the West Virginia Dental Conference
  - "Principals of Periodontal Therapy" 1950, 1955, 1958 (Box-folder 4.29)
    Read at the American Academy of Peroidontology meeting in Atlantic City, NJ.
  - "Problems and Relations of the Constituent Society with the Medical Profession" 1955 (Box-folder 4.30)
    Read at the American Dental Associations Management Conference. Chicago, IL
  - "Problems in the Teaching of Periodontology." 1937 (Box-folder 1937)
  - The Professional Gentleman and his Monopoly 1965 (Box-folder 4.32)
  - "Recent Advances in Dental Care" 1950 (Box-folder 4.33)
  - "A Suggested Method of Examination for Licensure." 1939 (Box-folder 4.34)
    Read at National Association of Dental Examiners Annual Meeting. Milwaukee, WI (See Folder 3.4)
  - "Survey of the Important Advances Made in Dental Education in the U.S. in the Last 50 Years." 1959 (Box-folder 4.3)
    Read at the International Conference of Dental Education. New York, NY (See Folder 3.38)
  - "Technical Procedures in Periodontology." (Box-folder 4.36)
  - "Techniques of Various Forms of Periodontal Therapy" 1956 (Box-folder 4.37)
    (See Folder 3.78)
  - "The Training of Teachers" 1951 (Box-folder 4.38)
  - "Two Centuries of Dentistry in Virginia" 1976 (Box-folder 4.39)
    Read at the Annual Meeting of the Virginia Dental Association. (See Folder 3.67, Audio on reel-to-reel)
  - "Vincent's Infection of the Mouth" 1938, 1942 (Box-folder 4.40)
    Written for a chapter in Samuel Gordon's book, Dental Science and Dental Art Updated in 1943.
  - "A Virginian Contributes" (Box-folder 4.41)
    Article written in response to J. Wilson Ames.
  - "What is Required of a Dental Teacher?" 1955 (Box-folder 4.42)
    Read at the 32nd Annual Meeting of the American Association of Dental Schools.
  - "You Face a Challenge" 1956 (Box-folder 4.43)
  - Untitled Addresses. (Box-folder 4.44)
  - Untitled Addresses 1928-1957 (Box-folder 4.45)
  - Untitled Addresses 1959-1973 (Box-folder 4.46)
- Newspaper Clippings and Press Releases. 1950-1979
  This series consists of clippings and press releases covering Lyons' professional career.
  - Undated clippings. (Box-folder 5.1)
    Mounted newsprint clippings.
  - Newspaper Clippings 1950-1959 (Box-folder 5.2)
    Mounted newsprint clippings. Topics include Lyons named Dean of School of Dentistry, President of the ADA, and the fluoridation campaign.
  - Newspaper Clippings 1960-1979 (Box-folder 5.3)
    Mounted newsprint clippings. Topics include awards won by Lyons, retirement from University, and philantrophy.
  - Press Releases 1951-1970 (Box-folder 5.4)
    This folder contains press releases from the American Dental Association and Virginia Commonwealth University. Subjects include Lyon's efforts at fluoridation, his demand for better dental education, and the naming of the Harry Lyons dental building at VCU.
- Newsletters, Bulletins and Journals 1951-1975
  This series contains journals, newsletters and bulletins regarding Lyons or featuring his writings.
  - Newsletters and Bulletins 1931-1975 (Box-folder 6.1)
    This folder contains bulletins and newsletters with information concerning Lyons from the American Dental Association, American Association of Dental Schools, Medical Society of Virginia, American Dental Trade Association, Kiwanis Club, National Conference of Christians and Jews, and the Rotary Club.
  - Journals and Publications. 1931-1987 (Box-folder 6.2)
    This folder contains journals that have articles written by or about Lyons.
    - Proceedings of the 8th Annual Meeting, American Association of Dental Schools. 1931 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Bulletin of the North Carolina Dental Society 1934 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 18, No 1
    - Proceedings of the 57th Annual Meeting of the National Association of Dental Examiners. 1939 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Proceedings of the 73th Annual Meeting of the National Association of Dental Examiners 1956 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - The Alpha Omegan 1941 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. XXV No. 1
    - The Alpha Omegan 1951 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. XLV No. 1
    - The Alpha Omegan 1956 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. L No. 3
    - The Alpha Omegan 1963 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. LVI No. 3
    - Bulletin, Medical College of Virginia 1952 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. XLIV No. 2
    - Bulletin, Medical College of Virginia 1955 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. LII No. 3
    - Bulletin, Medical College of Virginia 1970 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. LXVII No. 2
    - The Scarab, Alumni Association of MCV 1953 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 2 No. 3
    - The Fortnight Review of the Chicago Dental Society 1956 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 31 No. 9
    - Transactions of the Canadian Dental Association 1956 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Transactions of the American Dental Association 1957 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Revista Odontologica de Conception 1956 (Box-folder 6.2)
      Vol. 3 No. 4
    - 98th Annual Meeting, American Dental Association 1957 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Journal of the Canadian Dental Association 1960 (Box-folder 6.2)